Guide to the Lessons of the Sixties: A history of local Washington, DC activism for peace and justice from 1960-1975: Interviews, 2010-2019 MS2388
Special Collections Research Center, The George Washington University
- Interview: Rooney, Angela, 2013 February 19; MS2388
  Keywords provided by the donor for Angela Rooney interview: NORTH CENTRAL FREEWAY, NORTHEAST FREEWAY, THREE SISTERS BRIDGE, 38 MILES OF FREEWAYS PLANNED 10 WERE BUILT, COALITION OF BLACKS AND WHITES, BIOGRAPHY OF ANGELA, WTOP / CBS, LYING, CATHOLIC UNIVERSITY THEATER, BROOKLAND, FREEWAYS, WALTER TOBRINER, (?) DUNCAN, DISTRICT COMMISSIONERS, SAM ABBOTT, TAKOMA PARK, REV. JOHN MOTE, FEDERATION OF CIVIC ASSOCIATIONS, EDWARD SCOTT, REDLINING, SAM ABBOTT, INFILTRATION BY THE FBI, JULIUS HOBSON, MARION BARRY, PETER CRAIG, WASHINGTON POST, BRITISH ACCENT, AMERICAN LUNG ASSOCIATION, AIR POLLUTION, SUBWAY, HIGHWAY TRUST FUND, SLOGANS & MAPS, HERBLOCK, SONG ABOUT FREEWAYS, 1969 CITY COUNCIL MEETING, JOEL BROYHILL, SAM ABBOTT, JOHN HECHINGER, JACK EISEN, THE WASHINGTON POST, WHITE MAN'S ROADS…, KEN BURNS, BEER, THREE SISTERS BRIDGE, ELIZABETH "LIBBY" ROWE, COMMITEE OF 100, PETER CRAIG, BERNIE PRYOR OF BROOKLAND, EDWARD SCOTT, BLACK-WHITE COALITION, 1968 RIOTS, SAM ABBOTT, NATIONAL TRANSPORTATION COALITION, EVACUATION PLANS, NO END FOR THE FREEWAY ISSUE, METROPOLITAN COUNCIL OF GOVERNMENTS, POWER OF TECHNOLOGY, MARION BARRY, JULIUS HOBSON, ONE-MAN-BAND, LEWIS MUMFORD, JANE JACOBS, SAM ABBOTT, "BIGGEST GODDAMN POTHOLE".
- Interview: Roth Roberta Spalter and Roger Lesser, 2016 November 15; MS2388
  Roberta and Roger discuss some of their experiences in the movements of the 1960s.
  Keywords provided by the donor for Roberta Spalter-Roth and Roger Lesser inteview: Roberta Spalter-Roth, sociologist, Roger Lesser, studying the women's movement, studying the anti-war movement, Off Our Backs, Marilyn Webb, consciousness raising groups, Black Panther Movement, HEW, Federal Employees for a Democratic Society, federal employees demonstration with Dr. Spock, Institute for Policy Studies, IPS, 2016 Presidential election.
- Interview: Rubin, Larry, 2014 April 11; MS2388
  Larry Rubin is a life-long activist born into a progressive, secular Jewish family. Growing up in the McCarthy years, he attended the 1958 March on Washington and other political events as a teenager. While a student at Antioch in the early 60s he visited the SNCC Albany Project in Southwest Georgia, which was the immediate spur to his involvement in the civil rights movement, claiming "I never thought of not going South—It's what we do." He took his first job in Washington in 1962 as a community organizer at Southeast Neighborhood House. After other organizing stints in Kentucky and Mississippi, Larry returned permanently to Washington, DC, just as the major push for DC voting rights and Home Rule was gaining momentum. Working with SNCC leaders Marion Barry and Ivanhoe Donaldson, he participated in this successful campaign of the mid-to-late 70s. Larry also worked in the labor movement for many years as a lobbyist for United Electrical Workers and served four terms on the Takoma Park (MD) City Council.
  Keywords provided by the donor for Larry Rubin interview: Philadelphia, McCarthy, Teens Ahead, picketing Woolworth, 1958 March on Washington, Student Non-Violent Coordinating Committee (SNCC) Albany Project, Southeast Neighborhood House (SENH), Barry Farms, Conflict at SENH between systemic change and social work approach, Sharlene Kranz, Julius Hobson, HIlda Mason, Josephine Butler, Walter Washington, DC as Southern city, SNCC Holly Springs Project, Marion Barry, Frank Smith, Ivanhoe Donaldson, Charlie Cobb, Cleve Sellars, Pike County, Kentucky, 1965, Anne and Carl Braden, Southern Conference Education Project (SCEF), Margaret and Al McSurely, "You can't drop out of Antioch", SNCC workers in DC hired by Institute for Policy Studies (IPS), National Students Association (NSA), Central Intelligence Agency (CIA), Bob Avakian, Jack Anderson, Drew Pearson, Home Rule, United Electrical Workers, Bill Higgs, full employment, Friends of SNCC, Reflections on Ivanhoe Donaldson.
- Interview: Schwinn, Gerald, 2012 October 19; MS2388
  With an initial interest in civil rights and nuclear testing, Gerry Schwinn, a Baltimore native, found his way to a conference in Port Huron, Michigan in 1962 that proved to be seminal. The Port Huron Statement launched the Students for a Democratic Society (SDS), a key organization in the development of the anti-war movement and the New Left. Later that same year Gerry experienced the Cuban Missile Crisis up close in the military town of Hampton, Virginia, where the Norfolk Naval Base "almost sank from military activity." Needing a break, he joined the Peace Corps and spent 1963-65 in Nigeria, returning to Washington, DC just as the big anti-Vietnam War marches organized by SDS and other groups were beginning. Most of Gerry's anti-war work was done through the Committee of Returned Volunteers (CRV) founded by returnees of Peace Corps, International Volunteer Service (IVS), American Friends Service Committee (AFSC) among others. Gerry and John McAuliff of AFSC were founding members of this group, which soon came out in opposition to the Vietnam War on the premise that it undermined democratic traditions. CRV made history in 1970 when, during a massive demonstration after the invasion of Cambodia, several members took over the Peace Corps office for 36 hours and displayed a huge Viet Cong flag on the building within sight of the White House. Gerry Schwinn remains a committed activist in Washington, DC.
  Keywords provided by the donor for Gerry Schwinn interview: Cardozo High School, Peace Corps, Committee of Returned Volunteers (CRV), Home Rule, Incident in segregated Virginia, Cuban Missile Crisis, Viet Cong flag in 1970 demonstration, Trips to Vietnam and Cuba.
- Interview: Smith, Cliff, 2016 May 27; MS2388
  Former State Department Foreign Service Officer who was forced out of State due to his increasing opposition to the war in Vietnam and U.S. foreign policy and who became a lifelong activist for democracy.
  Keywords provided by the donor for Cliff Smith interview: State Department, Patriotic American, Democracy, Anti-war activist, Civil Rights activist, Equal rights, President Kennedy, University of Pennsylvania, Support of Greensboro sit-ins, Foreign Service Officer, Juarez, Mexico, Braceros, Everybody is equal, Iran, Teheran, Anti-war petition, Top secret clearance, Secretary of State, Operations Center in State Department, First anti-war march in April 1967, Pentagon March, 1854 Wyoming Ave, Federal Employees for A Democratic Society, Federal Employees Against the War in Vietnam, Signed Anti-war petition, New York Times article on anti-war petition, First Amendment Right, Resurrection City, Poor People's Campaign, Treaty of Guadalupe Hidalgo, Reies Tijerina, Tabriz Iran, State Department Open Forum for Young Professionals, Roundtable on Cuba, Peace Corps Volunteers, Draft Counseling, Conscientious Objector status for Peace Corp Volunteers, Moratorium, Anti-war petition in Iran, Left State Department in 1971, Becoming a hippie, Community Book store, Venceremos Brigade, 1854 Wyoming House for Federal Employee Activists, 1972 Arrests, NIMH Demonstration, I.F. Stone, WGTB, Embassy of Atlantis, Marxist Leninist Study Group, WGTB News Collective, Georgeton University, Shutdown WGTB, Fired WGTB staff 1975, Zodiac News Service, reported on AIM Inside BIA, Wounded Knee Live Broadcasts, Allende Overthrow News, Marxist Leninist Study Groups, Communism, Communist Party Marxist Leninist USA, US China People's Friendship Association, Trips to China, Expand Economic Democracy, Part of one movement for democracy, World Council of Churches, Anti-Ballistic Movement, Men re-thinking lives, Women ruling the world, Drugs in 1960's and 1970's, Hash in Iran, Interconnectedness of everything, Living in Washington, DC, Equal rights for women in DC, The value of humor, Cab driver, Tabriz Iran - on the route for hippies in Europe and into Iran.
- Interview: Smith, Frank, 2016 July 25; MS2388
  Frank Smith, born in Georgia, was a founding member of the Student Non-Violent Coordinating Committee. He came to Washington in the 1960s. He was elected to the Board of Education and the District of Columbia City Council where he served for 16 years. His passion for African-American history led to his work establishing the African-American Civil War Memorial.
  Keywords provided by the donor for Frank Smith interview: Arrived 1968, Institute for Policy Studies, SNCC, New Freedom Party, '62-'68 Mississippi organizer, Ivanhoe Donaldson, Marion Barry, King chance meeting April 1968, Adams-Morgan, SNCC ran the city, John Wilson, Hilda Mason, home rule, Marcus Raskin, Charlotte Bunche Weeks, IPS, Arthur Waskow, School Board, self-help housing, 1971, rent control legislation, First Right to Purchase legislation, changing neighborhood, meetings, Adams-Morgan Organization AMO, affluence, unions, better schools, Julius Hobson, Dunbar for the elites, police violence, Nation of Islam, Black Panthers, lived through a revolution, growing middle class, Museum of African-Americans and the Civil War.
- Interview: Solomon, Norman, 2013 Ocrtober 30; MS2388
  DC-area high school civil rights and anti-war activist targeted by FBI in the 1960s and early 1970s; later, noted author of numerous anti-war and press criticism books, anti-war filmmaker ("War Made Easy"), founding director of the Institute for Public Accuracy and co-founder of the national group RootsAction.org.
  Keywords provided by the donor for Norman Solomon interview: Montgomery County Md. high school activism, anti-war and anti-racism activism, "War Made Easy" (book and movie), Institute for Public Accuracy, ExposeFacts.org, Roots Action, FAIR (Fairness and Accuracy in Reporting), Washington D.C., Wilmington DE, USAID (U.S. Agency for International Development), India, Silver Spring Maryland, Calcutta India poverty, Eastern Junior High School, Montgomery Blair High School, Montgomery County Sentinel, Spiro Agnew, FBI file, housing segregation, Summit Hills apartments in Silver Spring, ACCESS (Action Coordinating Committee to End Segregation in the Suburbs), Rep. Carlton Sickles, George Mahoney, Spiro Agnew, ACCESS, FBI file, Adlai Stevenson, Civil rights, McCarthy era, Student Union, Montgomery County Student Alliance, Edgar Hoover, Student rights, military recruiters, anti-war activities, Portland Oregon, FBI, "Wanted: A Humane Education", grape boycott, Farm Workers Union, Brint Dillingham, Debby Barger (Hanrahan), Compeers, Freedom House, Bethesda Maryland, counterculture, marijuana, police harassment, Vietnam, spray painted antiwar slogans, "revolt for peace", President Richard Nixon, SDS (Students for a Democratic Society), Cathy Wilkerson, Weather Underground, Bill Higgs, Liberation News Service, SDS, Democratic National Convention 1968, Cathy Wilkerson, Montgomery County, Bill Higgs, Free school Park Road, hashish, Steve Miller Band, mental health issues, register with draft board, Draft card, conscientious objector status, 1-A status, California, San Francisco Bay Weekly, Washington Post, Roger Farquhar editor, Montgomery County Sentinel, business page editor, religious page editor, Brint Dillingham, ABM (anti-ballistic missile system), Debby Barger, Washington Free Press, grape boycott, Joe Forer, Ober Law, FBI surveillance, U.S. Department of Health Education and Welfare HEW), Federal Employees for a Democratic Society, Student Alliance, Reed College, Earth Day, Berkeley California, Jackson State, Kent State, Draft lottery, Blair High School, Ramparts Magazine, National Student Association, CIA, Dr. Howard Levy, Carlos Van Leer, White House vigils, Cedar Lane Unitarian Church, Dick Gregory, Gray Panthers, "War Made Easy", Bernard Fall, Gulf of Tonkin, Third Reich, Saddam Hussein, Iraq, Institute for Public Accuracy, Rep. Nick Rahall, U.N. weapons inspectors, Student Alliance, Brint Dillingham, Washington Post, Portland Oregon, obstacles to student activism today, National Security Agency (NSA) surveillance, climate change, Washington Star, Washington Post, Nicholas von Hoffman, March on Pentagon, May Day 1971 arrests, ACLU, General Colin Powell, Lawrence Wilkerson, Democracy Now!, Iraq war, Institute for Public Accuracy, Dick Cheney, Donald Rumsfeld, Scott Ritter, NSA spying, Senator Dianne Feinstein, Baghdad, Nick Rahall, Rep. Richard Gephardt, SDS, Chicago, Democratic National Convention 1968, counter-inaugural 1969, Nicholas von Hoffman, France uprising 1968, "Made Love, Got War", Charles Reich, "The Greening of America", hippie, corporate power, militarism, violent revolution, New Age revolution, working in the system illusion, in the streets, labor unions, Alan Grayson, Dennis Kucinich, Barbara Lee, Richmond California, Chevron, Green Party, Bernie Sanders, Occupy movement.
- Interview: Stockard, Susan, 2017 February 16; MS2388
  Susan Stewart Stockard, now married to Jim, was a student at the first school integrated in Arlington County and the state of Virginia. Her family was part of the activist group that worked with Stockard.
  Keywords provided by the donor for Susan Stewart Stockard interview: James Stockard daughter-in-law, Arlington County Virginia, School integration, Stratford Junior High School 1957-1960, First integrated 1959, Susan's parents, 1959 big event, First day of school, Police and reporters, Susan is interviewed, 5 African American students, Arlington segregated neighborhoods, Arlington segregated churches, Mother attends Howard University, Girls ridicule Susan, No school dances, All-white cheerleaders, A few black athletes, 3 years later integration, Defenders of State Sovereignty sent a letter.
- Interview: Stockard Family, James G., 2017 February 16; MS2388
  The three adult children of James G. Stockard ( James G. Stockard Jr, Ruth Stockard Flynn, and Janet Stockard de Merode ) discuss their father and what it was like growing up in Arlington Virginia while their father was a civil rights activist. Stockard served on the Arlington County School Board from 1955 to 1968. This was a time of great turmoil over integration. Stockard's was a wise, tolerant, and pro-integration voice.
  Keywords provided by the donor for James Stockard Family interview: James G. Stockard, leading civil rights leader, Janet Stockard DeMarott 1955-1967, Ruth Stockard Flynn 1950s, James G. Stockard Jr. 1950s, 1956 PTA school committee, Implementing Brown v Board, Election 1955 nasty, Father ran for school committee, Election night, Pro-integration member majority, Virginia bans elected school boards, Harry Byrd, Stockard lobbies for elected board, Southern Baptist, Voting with Jesus and Jefferson, 1961 Baptist church refuses entry to black family, Stockards leave church, Defenders of State Sovereignty…, George Lincoln Rockwell, Nazi Party, Separate seating in county court, Nasty kids, Phone threats, Cross burning, Nazi pamphlet about Stockard, Nadine John Stockard, Odd Arlington school districts, Washington-Lee High School integration.
- Interview: Tabor, Michael (Jews for Urban Justice), 2015 August 28; MS2388
  An activist and organizer in the Washington, D.C. area for more than five decades on a wide array of issues, including free speech rights, opposition to the Vietnam War, for racial justice and for sustainable agriculture. In the first interview, Michael describes his work over several years with Jews for Urban Justice, including their work challenging Jewish apartment owners and the Jewish community leadership in perpetuating slum housing, redlining and other housing inequities, and their work with Arthur Waskow organizing the first Freedom Seder. The second interview covers his civil rights and anti-Vietnam War organizing in the Maryland suburbs, including active involvement in local Congress of Racial Equality (CORE) and Students for a Democratic Society (SDS) chapters, his activism while working at the Department of Health, Education and Welfare (HEW), his work with the Jewish Renewal Movement, and the beginnings of his long-term ownership of Licking Creek Bend Farm and its focus on sustainably grown produce.
  Keywords provided by the donor for Michael Tabor - Jews for Urban Justice (JUJ) interview: working class upbringing, mother a bookkeeper, Chelsea Hotel, Brooklyn, Queens, Fort Green, Parsons Junior High School, public school education, SUNY – State University of New York, WASPs – White Angle-Saxon Protestants, Free Speech Movement, underground newspaper, activist grandmother and mother, conservative and orthodox Judaism, Fort Green Jewish Center, HUAC – House Unamerican Activities Committee, censorship, University of Maryland Graduate School, Route 1 segregated in 1963, Uncle Tom's Cabins – Beltsville, CORE – Congress of Racial Equality, SDS – Students for a Democratic Society, activism, sit-ins, segregation, Freedom Summer 1964, ERAP – Education Research Action Program, Joint SDS-CORE project, JUJ – Jews for Urban Justice, federal worker – 1968, discussion groups, ACCESS – Action Coordinating Committee to End Segregation, in the suburbs, restrictive covenants, housing, Jews in real estate, Jewish slumlords, work vs ethics, JUJ – first wave fight against racism in north, Sharlene Kranz, militancy, confrontation, no compromise, Freedom Now, Poor People's Campaign – 1968, 2000 sandwiches, Arthur Waskow, JCC – Jewish Community Center – shower facilities, Arnold Sternberg, Mother's Day Welfare Rights March, Coretta Scott King, Grape Boycott – 1968, Joseph Danzansky, Giant Food, Harold White, Guardian Savings, redlining, Arthur Waskow, consciousness raising group, white skin privilege, riots – 1968, ghetto tour, Camp Moshava, Habonim Dror, Brint Dillingham, George Wiley, Channing Phillips, Freedom Seder, JCRC – Jewish Community Relations Council Urban Affairs Committee, Sharon Rose, reparations, James Forman, guerrilla theater, shmattas for shvartzes – rags for blacks, public housing law – 1966, Jews acting as Christians, new left, exploiting others, Topper Carew, Balfour Brickner, Lincoln Temple, Freedom Seder 1969 800 people, Let all who are hungry come and eat, Baltimore Freedom Seder, George Malzone, middle east, Israel-Palestine, controversy, Jewish social justice group, Arthur Waskow, many similar groups, first national conference, Radnor PA 1970, The Jewish Urban Guerrilla, confrontational, Jews United for Justice, Diaspora Kibbutz – 1971, healthy organic food, 18th and Columbia farmer's market, activist, Jamie Raskin, Bernie Sanders, neocons, speak up against tyranny.
- Interview: Tabor, Michael (Challenging Segregation), 2018 March 28; MS2388
  Biography provided by the donor: An activist and organizer in the Washington, D.C. area for more than five decades on a wide array of issues, including free speech rights, opposition to the Vietnam War, for racial justice and for sustainable agriculture
  Information provided by the donor: Michael Tabor discusses his civil rights and anti-Vietnam War organizing in the Maryland suburbs, including active involvement in local Congress of Racial Equality (CORE) and Students for a Democratic Society (SDS) chapters, his activism while working at the Department of Health, Education and Welfare (HEW), his work with the Jewish Renewal Movement, and the beginnings of his long-term ownership of Licking Creek Bend Farm and its focus on sustainably grown produce.
  Keywords provided by the donor: Michael Tabor, Mike Tabor, 1960-75, organizer, civil rights, anti-vietnam war movement, grape boycott, first Jewish new-left political group in U.S., Norman Thomas, parents democrats, Army-McCarthy hearings, 1950s fear, low-income public housing – Fort Greene in Brooklyn, working class background, SUNY-Oneonta, underground newspaper, Pete Seeger sang – 1961, University of Maryland, March on Washington – 1963, segregated restaurants, Adelphi – sundown town, CORE – Congress of Racial Equality, voter registration in North Carolina, local SDS chapter, Cedar Heights, Freedom House, SCLC, Martin Luther King Jr., Prince George's County, CORE suit against school segregation, joint CORE/SDS/ERAP project against segregation, ACCESS – Action Coordinating Committee to End Segregation in the Suburbs, Julius Hobson, Jewish slumlords, Bel Air at Bowie, march around the Beltway against segregation, HUAC, Chuck Jones, George Lincoln Rockwell and Nazis, KKK, White Citizens Council chapter, social worker, fired for picketing Human Relations Commission, organizer for April 17 1965 march against the war, James Reeb, SSOC – Southern Students Organizing Committee, Fannie Lou Hamer, Aaron Henry, Mississippi Freedom Democratic Party, Democratic Convention – 1964, SNCC – Student Nonviolent Coordinating Committee, Bob Moses, John F Kennedy, corporate liberalism, Baker's Dozen organizing project - Columbia Heights, Catholic men's group, Phil Berrigan, Father McSorley, Pentagon sit-in against segregated housing, Robert McNamara, Brint Dillingham, Center for Emergency Support, white skin privilege, Arthur Waskow, Cathy Wilkerson, Tabor a new left socialist/Bookchin anarchist, George Wiley, FEDS – Federal Employees for a Democratic Society, HEW, The Condition of the Federal Employee and How to Change It, Thursday Discussion Group, ACLU support, grape boycott – targeted Giant Food, organizing in Jewish Community, Jews for Urban Justice, street theater, Rabbi Harold White, poured "blood of workers" on grapes, Jews for Urban Justice, Arthur Waskow, Freedom Seder, Community of Micah, Jewish Renewal Movement, Fabrengen, People's Peace Treaty, Madame Binh, peace treaty between Jewish community and Vietnam, raised money for medicine and trees, 1972 study group - communes, worker-run farm, Licking Creek, CAFOs – Concentrated Animal Feeding Operation, nuclear waste dump, farmer's market at 18th and Columbia Rd, apple cider to Florida and organic oranges from Florida to local co-ops like Fields of Plenty and Glut, elect local progressives.
- Interview: Treanor, William, 2017 April 20; MS2388
  Bill Treanor has been a Washington, DC fixture since the early 1960s, first as a student activist at Georgetown University, then as an organizer for SCLC, one of the great civil rights organizations of the 60s, later as an elected official to DC's first elected School Board and, finally, as an advocate for youth. A high school dropout himself, Bill served in the US Army before entering Georgetown University in 1963. His civil rights experience included staff work for the 1968 Poor Peoples' Campaign. He is best known for his long time leadership in support of youth services, which included the founding of Runaway House and the publication of Youth Today, a monthly national periodical for people working in the field.
  Keywords provided by the donor for William Treanor interview: Jesuit Richard Mc Sorley a major influence at Georgetown, Organizer in South with SCLC (Southern Christian Leadership Conference), Poor Peoples' Campaign, Resurrection City, National Youth Work Alliance, DC School Board, Marion Barry, Runaway House, Dupont Circle in the 1970s, On leadership, Anti-Freeway Fight, Hosea Williams and Ralph Abernathy- SCLC leaders at Resurrection City, Sammy Abbott and Reggie Booker – leaders in Anti-Freeway Fight, Debbie Shore, Sasha Bruce House, Lori Kaplan, Latin-American Youth Center.
- Interview: Tucker, Kitty, 2015 March 12 and 2015 August 28; MS2388
  (1944-2019) - Environmental, health and anti-nuclear activist who was a leader of the Washington, D.C. Karen Silkwood campaign and a key participant in the Washington, D.C. coalition to impeach President Nixon.
  Keywords provided by the donor for Kitty Tucker interview: Kitty Tucker, Karen Silkwood, Richard Nixon, impeachment.
- Interview: White, Harold, 2015 March 19; MS2388